Guide to the John Albok Photograph Collection 1928-1997 (bulk, 1930-1980) PR 1
New-York Historical Society
John Albok photograph collection
1928-1997 (bulk, 1930-1980)
New-York Historical Society
Albok, John, 1894-1982
PR 1
10.63 Linear feet (12 boxes)
Photographs of New York City street scenes and events
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Ilona Albok Vitarius, 1984-2006.
Arrangement
This collection is organized in three series:
Series I. Prints
Series II. Negatives
Series III. Documents
Biographical Note
John Albok was born in Munkacs, Hungary (present-day Ukraine) in 1894. The oldest of eleven children, he learned to be a tailor at age 13. He wanted to be an artist, however, and satisfied his artistic leanings through photography using a Kodak Brownie acquired in a trade for a pair of binoculars. During World War I he was drafted into the Hungarian Army and while behind the lines he photographed emaciated Russian captives.
After the war Albok learned that while he'd been away his two sisters had died of starvation and his father had committed suicide. Shattered, he decided to emigrate, leaving for the United States in 1921. Soon after he arrived in New York City he opened a tailor shop at 1392 Madison Avenue, at 96th Street, where he lived until his death. He photographed street scenes through his shop window and developed them at night, turning his shop into a darkroom.
Albok soon married a woman named Elona and had a daughter, also Elona. In 1929 a portrait of his daughter won him the Eastman Kodak Amateur Photo Contest. However, throughout the 1930s he was known only to his neighbors, who often paid him for family portraits, pet portraits, photographs of Hungarian events, or other neighborhood get-togethers. Then, in 1937, Albok was discovered by noted curator Grace Mayer (1901-1996) after he won a weekly photo contest sponsored by the New York Herald Tribune. In 1938, Mayer, who was instrumental in the re-discovery of Jacob Riis and built the photograph collection at the Museum of the City of New York, arranged to have Albok's work exhibited at MCNY in a show titled "Faces of the City."
After the show Albok's career picked up steam. His photograph subjects included leisure time in Central Park, the 1939-1940 World's Fair, New York street scenes during World War II, and later Greenwich Village and the Russian Orthodox Church, specifically St. Nicholas Cathedral on East 97th Street between Fifth and Madison Avenues. Albok had an aesthetic fascination with children, animals, and leisure activities; the majority of the New-York Historical Society's collection revolves around these subjects.
Albok died of cancer at Mt. Sinai Hospital on January 10, 1982, at the age of 87, a day before a retrospective of his work, "Tailored Images," opened at the Museum of the City of New York. At the time of his death he was survived by his wife and daughter. During his life his work had been exhibited at museums and galleries across the country and had been the subject of two films: "John Albok's New York," (1966) nominated for an Emmy, and "John Albok, Master Tailor," done for Swedish television (1979). After his death his work continued to be displayed in museums, galleries, as greeting cards, and on television. Numerous articles in art magazines and journals have also been written on Albok.
Related Materials
The Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections holds copies of two monographs on Albok: John Albok, 1894-1982; Through the Eye of the Needle, and John Albok: For the Children.
Albok's complete archive is estimated at 15,000 prints, of which approximately 1,400 are at New-York Historical Society. Museum of the City of New York, Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives at New York University, the Metropolitan Museum of Art, and the New York Public Library are other notable repositories for his prints. Several of Albok's photographs of New York soccer matches are at the National Soccer Hall of Fame, and Ilona Albok Vitarius still retains other prints and negatives.
Scope and Contents
The John Albok Collection almost exclusively comprises photographs of New York City, especially Manhattan. The collection is divided into three series: Prints; Negatives; Documents. As a whole the collection spans 1928-2006, but the primary years are 1930-1980, when virtually all the photographs were taken. The decades with the largest number of prints are the 1940s and 1950s.
Albok's fondest subject was Central Park, and the Society's Albok collection has hundreds of prints and negatives of the park from the late 1920s up until 1980. The Central Park pictures depict a variety of activities: picnics, artists, sports, birds such as herons, ducks, and pigeons, and winter snowfall among them. Many also depict the Central Park Conservatory Garden, opened in 1937, that runs along northern Fifth Avenue, a few blocks from where Albok lived. The remaining Central Park pictures are of trees, flowers and the reservoir. Albok also photographed numerous street scenes throughout the decades, particularly of his East Harlem neighborhood. His earlier neighborhood photographs delineate the Italian demographic of the area before the post-World War II Hispanic influx that led to the nickname Spanish Harlem or "El Barrio." Aside from East Harlem photographs there are also photos of 1960s Greenwich Village and landmarks such as Rockefeller Center, the United Nations, the Guggenheim Museum, and one photo of the Empire State Building. Other subjects include the 1939-1940 World's Fair, the Russian Orthodox Church, various Hungarian functions, animals, children, portraits done in his tailor shop/studio, and a few miscellaneous pictures that include skyscapes, building interiors, Mayor Fiorella LaGuardia at Madison Square Garden and Louis Lefkowitz at a soccer match. The Hungarian pictures include Hungarian picnics in Bohemian Park, Queens, and New Jersey. The New Jersey pictures were taken mostly at Bugacs Puszta, a farm in Dayton, New Jersey. According to Ilona Vitarius, the Bugacs Puszta was the first New York and New Jersey Hungarian Charity Association, founded in 1901. Bugacs may be a reference to "Bugac," small area of central Hungary; Puszta is the Hungarian word for steppes. Albok gave money to the organization and even made a 16mm film of its underprivileged children camps. The New-York Historical Society does not have this film footage.
Despite living in New York City for 60 years, Albok's known work includes few pictures taken outside Manhattan. The Society's Albok collection has little of other boroughs - none of Staten Island, a few of the Brooklyn Botanic Gardens, only the World's Fair and Bohemian Park in Queens, none of the Bronx. One oversized print is identified as Westchester county. The parade images the Society has are mainly of Labor Day parades. Albok did photograph numerous other labor demonstrations and parades, including May Day rallies in Union Square during the 1930s, however the Society does not have these prints. The Society's collection also has no prints of the 1964 World's Fair, none of any major city parades such as Easter, Thanksgiving Day, St. Patrick's Day, World Series or other sporting celebrations, or parades for dignitaries or visiting heads of state. It is unknown if Albok took such pictures. Overall the Society's Albok pictures of downtown are mainly of art sales in and around Washington Square Park and capture little of the folk scene of Greenwich Village. In addition, of the few pictures related to Vietnam in the collection, all but one are of pro-intervention rallies.
Separated Materials
The color slides from Series II are stored separately in Box 12 in cold storage and require advance notice to view.
Children.; Hungarians -- New York (State) -- New York.; Labor Day -- New York (State) -- New York.; Parades -- New York (State) -- New York.; Street photography.; Central Park (New York, N.Y.); New York (N.Y.) -- Photographs.; New York (N.Y.) -- Pictorial works.; New York (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs.; Gelatin silver prints.; negatives (photographs); Photographic prints.; Portraits.; Self-portraits; Slides (photographs).; Streets -- New York (State) -- New York.; New York World's Fair (1939-1940: New York, N.Y.) [111]
- Series I. Prints
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I. Prints includes largely black and white, with some color, prints of John Albok's photographs from 1928 - 1979. The primary subject is Central Park. Street scenes include East Harlem (E. 96th - E. 125th Streets) during the 1930s and 1940s; 1960s Greenwich Village; and landmarks, particularly Rockefeller Center. He also photographed Hungarian events in and around the city; parades and demonstations such as the Labor Day parades of the 1960s and Puerto Rican Day parades; the Russian Orthodox Church; 1939 World's Fair; studio portraits; and several prominent personalities such as Governor Herbert Lehman and Hon. Fiorello LaGuardia. One of the oversized printsfrom the World's Fair also has Eleanor Roosevelt. Albok had a strong aesthetic fascination with children and he has a quirky collection of animal photographs.
  The prints are arranged by subject, then sub-subjects where appropriate, then by approximate dates. It is important to note that the dates are not reliable. It appears most dates were supplied by Ilona Vitarius, and where she got them from is questionable. In many instances different prints of the same scene have as many as three different dates. For example, a print of a girl having her finger bandaged in Central Park is dated 1950 but a second print of the same scene is dated, on the back, 1953 and on the front, 1958. In another instance, a print of a Sikh couple in Central Park is dated mid-60s and a duplicate print is dated 1970. Researchers should use the dates as a guide but will have to do independent research to obtain accuracy.
  - Central Park
    - General, 1930-1979 (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
      General note
      See also oversize Box 6, folder 64
    - Animals, 1932-1979 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
      See also oversize Box 7, folder 65
    - Artists, 1938-1960 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      See also oversize Box 7, folder 66
    - Conservatory Garden, 1938-[1960] (Box 1, Folder 9)
      See also oversize Box 7, folder 67
    - Monuments and Statues, 1933-1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Reservoir, 1928-1970 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      See also oversize Box 7, folder 68
    - Sports and Games, 1939-1979 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      See also oversize Box 7, folder 69
    - Winter Scenes, 1933-[1973] (Box 1, Folder 13)
      See also oversize Box 7, folder 70
  - NYC Street Scenes
    - General, 1930-1979 (Box 2, Folder 14-15)
      See also oversize Box 8, folder 71
    - East Harlem, 1933-1980 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      See also oversize Box 8, folder 72
    - Greenwich Village, 1943-[1960] (Box 2, Folder 17)
      See also oversize Box 8, folder 73
    - Landmarks, 1942-1977 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      See also oversize Box 8, folder 74
    - Winter Scenes, 1936-1978 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      See also oversize Box 8, folder 75
    - Parades and Demonstrations - Labor Day Parade, 1960-1968 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      See also oversize Box 8, folder 76
    - Parades and Demonstrations - Puerto Rican Day Parade, 1963-1979 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Parades and Demonstrations - Vietnam, 1964-1971 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Parades and Demonstrations - World War II, 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Parades and Demonstrations - Other parades and demonstrations, 1961-1976 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Children
    - General, 1933-1978 (Box 3, Folder 25)
      See also oversize Box 9, folder 77
    - Babies, 1930-1978 (Box 3, Folder 26)
      See also oversize Box 9, folder 78
    - At Play, 1933-[1969] (Box 3, Folder 27)
      See also oversize Box 9, folder 79
    - School children, [1950-1979] (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Swimming, Bathing, and Water, 1930-1953 (Box 3, Folder 29)
      See also oversize Box 9, folder 80
  - Russian Orthodox Church
    - General, 1940-[1980] (Box 3, Folder 30)
      See also oversize Box 10, folder 81
    - St. Nicholas Cathedral - Building Shots, 1928-[1980] (Box 3, Folder 31)
      See also oversize Box 10, folder 82
  - World's Fair
    - World's Fair, 1939-1940 (Box 3, Folder 32)
      See also oversize Box 11, folder 83
  - Hungarians
    - Hungarians - New York, 1934-[1970] (Box 3, Folder 33)
      See also oversize Box 11, folder 84
    - Hungarian camps and farms - New Jersey, 1938-1939 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Animals
    - Animals, 1932-[1979] (Box 3, Folder 35)
      See also oversize Box 11, folder 85
  - Portraits
    - Portraits, 1943-[1979] (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Albok's Tailor Shop
    - Albok's Tailor Shop, 1932-1980 (Box 3, Folder 37)
      See also oversize Box 11, folder 86
  - Albok and Family
    - Albok and family, 1928-[1980] (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Politicians, 1940-1946 (Box 3, Folder 39)
      See also oversize Box 11, folder 87
    - Sky, 1933-1980 (Box 3, Folder 40)
      See also oversize Box 11, folder 88
    - Miscellaneous, 1929-[1969] (Box 3, Folder 41)
      See also oversize Box 11, folder 89
- Series II. Negatives
  Series II is primarily acetate, Kodak safety negatives, as well as color Kodak Ektachrome slides, of John Albok's photographs. The majority of the negatives are 2.5 x 2.5 inches though a few are strip negatives and others are 4 x 5 inches. The subject matter echoes the prints however the negatives include some later images not in prints, including more shots of East Harlem, the construction of Lincoln Center, more shots of the United Nations and a few shots of Adlai Stevenson. Not all the Society's negatives are in the print collection and vice versa; for example there is a substantial print collection from the 1939 World's Fair but only one negative.
  The negatives are arranged along similar subject headings as the prints but often not sub-divided further. The color slides are stored separately in cold storage and require advance notice to view.
  - Central Park
    - Central Park, 1936-1976 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - NYC Street Scenes
    - General, 1948-1979 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - East Harlem, 1945-1977 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Greenwich Village, 1946-1967 (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - Landmarks, 1945-1968 (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - Parks (not Central Park), 1948-1968 (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - Winter Scenes, 1960-1978 (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - Parades and Demonstrations, 1960-1978
      See cold storage Box 12 (color slides)
  - Children
    - Children, 1957-1977 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Russian Orthodox Church
    - Russian Orthodox Church, 1954-1978 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - World's Fair
    - World's Fair, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Animals
    - Animals, 1960-1966 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Portraits
    - Portraits, 1959-1978 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Albok's Tailor Shop
    - Tailor Shop, 1960-1978 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Albok and Family
    - Albok and Family, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Miscellaneous, 1947-1979 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Original envelopes in which negatives were sent to N-YHS (Box 4, Folder 57)
- Series III. Documents
  Series III comprises limited correspondence, articles, greeting cards and ephemera related to the work of John Albok, both during his life and posthumously. Many are photocopies. Documents from Albok's lifetime include notes for a speech given around the opening of his first exhibition, miscellaneous correspondence, Russian Orthodox Church ephemera, and two VHS video copies of the CBS documentary "John Albok's New York."
  - Documents appearing to have belonged to John Albok, 1938-1980 (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Albok's ephemera, 1940-1963 (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Articles on Albok, 1974-1994 (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - Albok obituaries, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Albok's films - VHS (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Greeting and post cards printed by other museums, 1990-1997 (Box 5, Folder 63)
- Oversize Material from Series I
  Arranged by subject then by folder, and within folder by approximate date.
  - Central Park
    - General, 1933-1962 (Box 6, Folder 64)
    - Animals, 1945-1950 (Box 7, Folder 65)
    - Artists, 1943-1960 (Box 7, Folder 66)
    - Conservatory Garden, 1937-1948 (Box 7, Folder 67)
    - Reservoir, 1932-1960 (Box 7, Folder 68)
    - Sports and Games, 1938-[1960] (Box 7, Folder 69)
    - Winter Scenes, 1933-[19703] (Box 7, Folder 70)
  - NYC Street Scenes
    - General, 1934-[1960] (Box 8, Folder 71)
    - East Harlem, 1943-1962 (Box 8, Folder 72)
    - Greenwich Village, 1945-[1960] (Box 8, Folder 73)
    - Landmarks, 1945-1962 (Box 8, Folder 74)
    - Winter Scenes, 1947-1950 (Box 8, Folder 75)
    - Parades and Demonstrations, 1939-1968 (Box 8, Folder 76)
  - Children
    - General, 1935-[1960] (Box 9, Folder 77)
    - Babies, 1934-1935 (Box 9, Folder 78)
    - At Play, 1943-1964 (Box 9, Folder 79)
    - Swimming, Bathing, and Water, 1934-1952 (Box 9, Folder 80)
  - Russian Orthodox Church
    - General, 1954-1963 (Box 10, Folder 81)
    - St. Nicholas Cathedral - Building Shots, 1957-1960 (Box 10, Folder 82)
  - World's Fair
    - World's Fair, 1939-1940 (Box 11, Folder 83)
  - Hungarians
    - Hungarians, 1938-1943 (Box 11, Folder 84)
  - Animals
    - Animals, 1940-1950 (Box 11, Folder 85)
  - Albok's Tailor Shop
    - Tailor Shop, 1938-1953 (Box 11, Folder 86)
  - Miscellaneous
    - NY Politicians, 1936 (Box 11, Folder 87)
    - Sky, 1932-1962 (Box 11, Folder 88)
    - Miscellaneous, 1929=1963 (Box 11, Folder 89)